hey what's up guys My Name Is AO welcome
back to my C++ series So today we're
going to be talking about control flow
statements and really this is going to
be a continuation of last week's episode
so if you haven't seen that episode
about loops definitely check that out
there'll be a link in the description
below control flow statements work with
loops so in other words they kind of
give us a little bit more control as to
how these Loops actually run we've kind
of got three main control flow
statements that we can use continue
break and return and they do different
things continue can only be used inside
a loop and basically continue says go to
the next iteration of this Loop if there
is one otherwise it'll just end the loop
breake is primarily used in Loops
however it also appears in switch
statements and basically break just says
get out of the loop so end the loop and
finally return is probably the most
powerful one if you want to consider it
that way because return will just get
out of your function entirely so if
you're in a function and you hit a
return keyword you will exit the
function of course for functions which
actually need to return a value Val when
you type in return you can't just have
return by itself return by itself is
only for void functions if your function
needs to return a value when you type in
return you need to supply it with a
value all right not much else to say
really let's just jump in and take a
look at some examples so this is the
program that we had in the last episode
we just give that a run you'll see we
have Hello World printing a bunch of
times and then of course we had a bit of
a while loop which nothing going to do
while loop that does nothing I'll just
get rid of some of these because we
don't really need them the only one that
I'll keep from our previous program is
pretty much that for Loop so the first
control flow statement that we'll look
at is continue continue will skip to the
next iteration of the for Loop so if I
write continue over here just like this
it will actually not impact the behavior
of the full loop at all because that is
already the end of the for Loop when it
hits that line it's going to continue to
the next iteration anyway so this
doesn't modify the behavior at all
however if I do something like if I mod
2 equals zero and then have a continue
there and run my program you'll see the
basically what's happening is it's
skipping every second iteration starting
with the first one so a better way to
illustrate this is probably to include
some kind of value so instead of just
logging hello world we can also log the
actual I variable to see what index is
currently at and if I write that and I
hit F5 you can see that our hello world
statement only runs at odd iterations in
other words when I is zero it's not
going to run because of course zero mod
Z is zero so it's going to continue
because this if statement is true
otherwise when I is one we're going to
get log when I is two we're not and when
I is three we are and then when I is
four we're not and then of course I
never hits five because when it hits
five we do not do the for Loop because
this statement says that I must be less
than five we could also change this to
something a bit more simple such as if I
is greater than two continue so
basically what should happen here is
when I is Zer and I is 1 and I is 2 it
should print out our log as well as what
I is however when I is three or four it
shouldn't so if we run that you'll see
we we get hell World printing three
times great so that's pretty much it for
continue I mean all it's going to do is
when continue gets hit it will skip to
the next iteration the full loop if we
actually debug this by putting a break
point here this will give you some more
insight so you can see here I is zero
which of course is not going to trigger
this so it's going to go down to log and
log and everything will be fine same for
when I is 1 and I is 2 however as soon
as I hits 3 and 3 is greater than two
we're going to go to continue which
means that if I hit F10 right now
instead of moving down to log you can
see it actually jumps back up to the
start of the for Loop and it will it
will do i++ and it will evaluate our
condition and then jump back here and of
course in this case it's going to be the
exact same behavior all right fantastic
that's continue sorted let's take a look
at break so if I just replace this code
with break it's going to appear to act
the same way you can see that we get 0 1
2 and we don't get anything else however
if I go back to my first example of if
I'm mod 2 = 0 and hit F5 you can see we
actually get absolutely nothing printing
now perhaps a little bit of a better
example here is to actually print the
first value so I'll just do I + 1 Mod
2al 0 if we quickly replace this with
continue just so you can see what's
happening here you can see that instead
of going odd numbers now it's going even
numbers so we get 0 two and four
printing so if I replace this now with
break what's actually going to happen is
it's just going to print that first one
because as soon as it hits that brake
statement that's it that Loop is over
game over for that Loop if we place a
break point over over here and we hit F5
you'll see the first time of course the
if statement is not going to be true so
we don't break but then the second time
we run through this full loop and this
is true when we hit break guess what if
I hit F10 right now we jump straight out
of the for Loop into the next line of
code so that's it break breaks our full
loop completely and of course these kind
of control flow statements inside Loops
apply to all Loops so full Loops while
Loops do wire Loops they work the same
in all Loops all right then the final
one we have is return now this is aun
function that has to return an integer
so we can't just type in return we have
to return something if we try and do
something like this and we hit contr F7
it's going to fail because you can see
it's telling us that main function must
return a value because the Declaration
States it has to return an integer so I
could do something like a return zero
zero of course is a valid integer and if
I run this code it's actually going to
immediately appear to close our program
because of course we never get to the
stdc and.get statement which is the
statement that keeps our window open
because it's expecting us to provide
input so if I again put a breakpoint
here and run my program you'll see the
first time it's fine it'll log Holo
world and we do actually get that Hol
World logging up here then the second
time when I hit return zero that's it
look at that it jumps right to that end
curly bracket because this function is
over now one other thing to note with
the return statement is that you don't
have to use return inside a loop the
same way that you have to with continue
and break return can be written anywhere
so I could do something like if five is
greater than 8 return Z and of course I
have to provide a value in this case
because this function returns an integer
so return not necessarily inside a loop
can be absolutely anywhere in your code
you also don't even have to have an if
statement you could have something like
this but of course in this case there is
no circumstance under which this line
would get triggered so this is actually
known as dead code and some compilers
especially in other languages will
actually restrict you from writing code
like this because I mean at this point
you might as well just delete this line
it's never going to get called so that's
pretty much it as far as control flow
statements go return can be used
anywhere and it will basically just exit
the function remember of course if your
function has to return a value then
return has to give it a value to return
these control flow statements basically
form the basis of how how your flow goes
so paired with loops and if statements
and like all of these control flow
statements that is essentially the logic
of programming those are the tools you
have access to to control the flow of
your program basically which line gets
executed next right those tools if
statements and conditionals like that
loops and control flow statements that
is it that is the only thing that can
modify the behavior of your program
short from you actually writing into the
instruction pointer don't do that maybe
as this series progresses and we start
actually writing applications I'll be
referencing all of these control flow
statements all the time and showing you
examples of where they're used and how I
can use them as well as probably showing
you examples about how I can write the
same code but without using them or with
using a different statement so if you
want some more more concrete examples of
how they actually work just stay tuned
to this series and in future episodes
when we actually start writing stuff
we're definitely going to cover this
because again this is one of the
fundamental building blocks of writing
an application but anyway I hope you
guys enjoyed this episode if you did
please hit that like button follow me on
Twitter and Instagram Link in the
description below if you really enjoyed
this video and you want to show your
support and make sure that more of these
awesome videos get made you can support
me on patreon.com Theo again link will
be in the description below next
time I've got quiet the episode for you
guys next time goodbye
[Music]